Guide to the Roe Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Roe family papers
1802-1977
MS 774
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
77.25
(164 boxes)
The papers contain family correspondence, missionary correspondence, family papers, diaries, sermons, printed works, photoprints, and other materials documenting the lives and careers of Alfred Cox Roe, Emma Wickham Roe, Mary Abigail Roe, Walter Clark Roe, Mary Wickham Roe, Joseph Wickham Roe, Henry Roe Cloud, and several other Roe relatives. The Roe family papers have extensive material on family life, specifically concerning such subjects as relations between brothers and sisters and parents and children, courtship, marriage, stepmothering, health and illness, old age, death, and finances. The papers also document the educational, missionary, and pastoral careers of several members of the Roe family and the Indian mission work of the Women's Board of Domestic Missions of the Reformed Church in America.
Roe family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marjorie Page Schauffler, 1975; Elizabeth Schauffler Lyman, 1983; Elizabeth Schauffler Lyman, Peter Page Schauffler, and Richard Manvel Schauffler, 1985; and Dorothy North, 2005.
Associated Materials
Wickham Family Papers (MS 773), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library); Page Family Papers (MS 772), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library); Elizabeth Page Harris Papers (MS 771), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library); Schauffler Family Papers (MS 1389), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library).
Arrangement
Arranged in twelve series: I. Family Correspondence, 1832-1960. II. Family Papers, 1846-1977. III. Diaries, 1856-1940. IV. Sermons, 1865-1911. V. Printed Works, 1849-1939. VI. Family Photographs, 1861-1960. VII. Henry Roe Cloud Papers, 1907-1952. VIII. Missionary Correspondence, 1897-1942. IX. Missionary Papers, 1886-1941. X. Missionary Photographs, 1860-1940. XI. Indian Book Collection, 1870-1956. XII. Roe Addition, 1802-1970.
Scope and Contents
The Roe Family Papers document the lives of many descendants of Peter Elting Roe and Susan Williams Roe, with the majority of the papers relating to the immediate family of Alfred Cox Roe. The material spans the dates 1802-1977, with bulk dates of 1860-1930. Marjorie Page Schauffler, granddaughter of Alfred Cox Roe, and her children, Elizabeth Dudley Schauffler Lyman, Peter Page Schauffler, and Richard Manvel Schauffler, donated the Roe Family Papers to Yale University in December 1975, January 1983, and January 1985. Significant related material can be found in the Wickham Family Papers (Ms Gr 773) and the Page Family Papers (Ms Gr 772).
The Roe Family Papers are part of a group of five related family collections, the others being the Wickham Family Papers, Page Family Papers, Elizabeth Page Harris Papers, and Schauffler Family Papers. In order to ensure that correspondence to and from the same individuals is kept together, a hierarchical system of arrangement has been adopted. For example, Elizabeth Merwin Roe Page's correspondence with her grandparents is found in the Wickham Family Papers; her correspondence with her parents, brother, and sister is found in the Roe Family Papers; and her correspondence with her husband and children is found in the Page Family Papers.
There are eleven series and one addition to the Roe Family Papers. Series I, Family Correspondence, contains all personal correspondence written or received by members of the Roe family between 1832-1960. Series II, Family Papers, consists of a variety of material relating to family members. Diaries kept by Alfred Cox Roe, Joseph Wickham Roe, Mary Abigail Roe, Mary Wickham Roe, and Walter Clark Roe are found in Series III. Series IV contains sermons by Alfred Cox Roe and Walter Clark Roe. The novels of Edward Payson Roe comprise about two-thirds of Series V, Printed Works. Portraits of many family members are contained in Series VI, Family Photographs. The correspondence of Henry Roe Cloud, the adopted Indian son of Walter Clark Roe and Mary Wickham Roe, can be found in Series VII, Henry Roe Cloud Papers. The last four series in the Roe Family Papers are all related to the missionary activities of Walter Clark Roe and Mary Wickham Roe. Correspondence concerning their work among the Indians is located in Series VIII, Missionary Correspondence. Series IX, Missionary Papers, contains a variety of material treating mission work and Indian life. Series X, Missionary Photographs, consists of photographs of Indians, missionaries, and missions. Series XI, Indian Book Collection, contains books owned by Walter Clark Roe and Mary Wickham Roe. The Addition to the Roe Family Papers has been divided into six series: Family Correspondence, Family Papers, Printed Works, Family Photographs, Henry Roe Cloud Papers, and Missionary Papers.
Series I, Family Correspondence, contains chronologically arranged correspondence of the Roe family, primarily documenting the lives and activities of Alfred Cox Roe, Emma Wickham Roe, and their children. The correspondence in Series I is divided into four major segments. The first covers the years 1832-1859 and contains correspondence of Emma Wickham and Alfred Cox Roe. The second group covers the period 1860-1880, from Alfred and Emma's marriage to the time when their two older children reach adulthood. The third group of letters spans the years 1880-1915 and centers on the Roe children and their Roe cousins, while the last covers the period from approximately 1915 to 1960 and concerns the later lives of the Roe children.
The first significant group of letters (Boxes 1-2, folders 1-57) consists of the correspondence of Alfred Cox Roe and Emma Wickham Roe prior to their 1860 courtship and marriage. Most of this material concerns Emma Wickham. Correspondents include several Porter relatives, particularly grandfather Moses Porter, uncle Eleazar Porter, and aunt Lucretia Porter Snell. (See also the Wickham Family Papers for additional material.) There is also a substantial group of letters by cousin Moses Porter Snell. Those written from Amherst College in 1857-1859 contain descriptions of college life and studies, as well as discussions of religious and personal topics. Cousin A. Moss Merwin's letters detail his studies and concerns as a student at Williams College. Emma Wickham's relatives are also frequent correspondents. Abigail Wickham's letters contain family news and religious advice. The letters of George Stebbins and Esther Wickham Stebbins describe their experiences in Missouri and Illinois during the 1840's and 1850's.
In the 1850's there are many letters from female friends, including Caroline Anderson, Mary P. Jones, Cordelia Sergeant, and Lucy Barrett, a student at Mt. Holyoke. All of these women became teachers, and their correspondence provides information. on women's education in the pre-Civil War era. The letters also discuss religion, social life, books, and current events. Other correspondents include Emily H. Craven and Edward Payson Roe. Roe was a student at Burr and Burton Academy, of which Emma's father, Joseph D. Wickham, was principal. Roe's letters, written in 1858-1859, contain references to Emma's visits at the Roe home at Cornwall on the Hudson.
There is much less material concerning Alfred Cox Roe prior to 1860. Correspondents include cousins Preston Bruen and E.H. Williams; family friend and New York University founder Samuel H. Cox; and South American missionary Jacob B. Sands. There are perhaps fifteen letters from Artemus Dean of Amherst College and M.M. Vail of New York City. Topics include politics, abolitionism, Dean's experience as a tutor for a Virginia family, and the education of women.
With the exception of a few business letters, there is almost no correspondence from the period of Alfred's first marriage to Caroline Powell Childs. There are no letters written by Caroline Childs Roe and just one 1845 letter addressed to her by Alfred. Her ill-health is mentioned in several letters of Edward Payson Roe.
In October, 1860, Alfred Cox Roe married Emma Wickham. The second group of correspondence dates from 1860 to approximately 1880 (Boxes 2-4, folders 58-130) and primarily concerns the couple and their children.
There is relatively little professional correspondence, but information on the career of Alfred Cox Roe as an educator, Civil War chaplain, and minister can be found in the personal letters. This group of letters contains letters by Dr. Howard Crosby of the American. Christian Commission, a few letters by parishioners, and copies of his contracts with various congregations. (For further information, see also Series II, Family Papers, Boxes 18-19).
Family correspondents in this section include Roe siblings Edward Payson Roe, John Peter Roe, Susan Elizabeth Roe Caldwell, and Mary Abigail Roe. Most of their letters date from the Civil War period and are concerned with family news and financial arrangements. An 1879 series of letters by Mary Abigail Roe describes her European tour.
Most of the correspondence in these two decades concerns Alfred and Emma, beginning with a small series of their lengthy and frank courtship letters. (Box 2, folders 57-62). Topics include Alfred's unhappiness with his mentally unbalanced first wife, his hopes for intimacy with Emma, his strained relationship with the two older children, and financial worries. Emma's letters are comparatively brief. A stepchild herself, she comments on the difficulties of becoming a stepmother. Both correspondents frequently discuss religion and the importance of divine guidance in personal affairs.
There are few letters from the first three years of the marriage, but the volume of correspondence increases during Alfred's 1864-1865 service as a Union Army chaplain. These letters contain news concerning Alfred's financial and career uncertainties. The couple openly express regret at their long separation. For example, an 1864 letter of Emma's describes her delight at Alfred's approaching furlough and mentions her wish to become pregnant again.
The Roe children are another important subject for discussion. Alfred's absence increased the difficulty of Emma's position as stepmother to the two older children, Frank Childs Roe and Susan Williams Roe. The letters frequently comment on Frank's resistance to Emma and his dislike of her. Emma's efforts to deal with Susan were frustrated by the child's mental abnormality. Letters of May and June, 1865 detail her symptoms and possible treatments, illustrating the nature of nineteenth-century responses to mental illness. Susan's illness is mentioned in subsequent years and the collection contains several letters written by her, including four from Willard Asylum for the Insane, where she died in 1873.
Most of the relatively few letters from the 1870's are written by Alfred Cox Roe and describe his ministerial career. Letters from Lowell, Massachusetts in 1870 allude to his attempts to organize his congregation and to include working-class Presbyterians in parish activities, a move resented by some parishioners. For additional information about family life and Alfred Roe's ministerial experiences, see the Wickham Family Papers.
The third and largest group of letters covers the years between 1880 and approximately 1915 (Boxes 4-10, folders 131-325). Although the correspondence between Alfred and Emma diminishes, their children become important correspondents and there are also letters from Roe relatives.
The few Edward Payson Roe letters discuss family news. Mary Abigail Roe's letters contain personal news, religious advice, and accounts of her activities as a teacher of natural history at Los Angeles College. Letters from the family of Alfred's younger brother James Gilbert Roe appear after James' move to Texas in 1883, a transfer prompted by his bankruptcy in the previous year. Correspondents from this branch include James Gilbert and his wife Caroline Clark Roe, and their children, William Edgar, Elizabeth C., Irene, Pierre, and James, all of whom correspond with their brother, Walter Clark Roe, a teacher at the Hill School in Pennsylvania, as well as with their cousins.
James Gilbert Roe's financial crisis affected his entire family, and letters of Alfred Cox Roe, Edward Payson Roe, John Peter Roe, and Samuel H. Caldwell detail these financial concerns (Box 4, folders 129-138 and Box 5). As a result of James's bankruptcy, Alfred's school in Cornwall failed in 1882, although he went on to found two more schools. Letters to James describe the schools' organization, curricula, and funding difficulties. There are also letters from pupils and their parents.
The children of Alfred Cox Roe are frequent correspondents during the 1880's. There is relatively little correspondence concerning Frank Childs Roe, and most of that dates from 1886-1889, when he was a patient at Fordham Hospital for the Incurable, where he subsequently died. The letters of Caroline Powell Roe Landon contain news and religious commentary. After separating from her husband in 1892, she became a Presbyterian missionary in rural Vermont, and her letters to Alfred describe her work and discuss such topics as preaching techniques and Biblical commentaries. Elizabeth Merwin Roe's letters describe a series of positions as companion and governess which she held between 1881 and her marriage to Alfred Rider Page in 1886. Mary Wickham Roe's letters often comment upon her teaching positions, first at New York State Normal School and then, beginning in 1885, at the Hill School in Pottstown, Pennsylvania.
Mary's cousin Walter Clark Roe also taught there and education and books are frequent topics in their letters. Their formal courtship begins in 1882 and continues until their marriage in 1887 (Boxes 4-6). The length of the correspondence is partially accounted for by their fear that marriage between first-cousins would be sinful. For example, in an 1884 letter Mary describes her conflicting feelings and suggests that they return to a "friendly" relationship. Letters of congratulation on their December 1886 engagement mention the rarity of first-cousin marriage and offer the couple religious reassurance. Other subjects in these courtship letters include religion and the possibility of Walter's studying for the ministry.
Letters of the 1880's and 1890's contain much information on the health of the two families. Between 1886 and 1890, William Edgar Roe, Walter Clark Roe, James Roe, Pierre Roe, and Frank Childs Roe all contracted tuberculosis; the latter three died of the disease. Symptoms, treatments, and family reactions to the illness are all important topics during this period, especially in the letters of Mary Wickham Roe after Walter was stricken in 1889 (Box 7).
In 1890 Mary and Walter moved to Ft. Worth, Texas for health reasons. Ordained in 1892, Walter served in the Dallas-Ft. Worth area for some years, but the Roes became interested in the missionary work being done at Colony, Oklahoma, by Frank Hall Wright, and Walter took charge of the mission there in 1897. The Roes' professional correspondence is located in Series VIII, Missionary Correspondence, but their personal letters also contain much information about conditions at Colony and its daily operations. Additional material can be found in the letters of Elizabeth Merwin Roe Page, always called Lillie, who served as Field Secretary to the Women's. Executive Committee of the Reformed Church in America from 1903-1813 and who visited Colony several times. Her letters are usually undated and these have been placed in Boxes 14-15, folders 420-52. (For additional information, see also the Page Family Papers.)
The third section of correspondence also contains many letters by Joseph Wickham Roe, beginning with notes describing his school life and activities at Burr and Burton, the Hill School, and Yale. After his 1895 graduation, Joseph's letters are mainly brief announcements of news, travel plans, and financial information, However, the Addition to the Roe Papers contains 1902 courtship letters written by his first wife, Nellie Allen Roe, who died six weeks after their marriage, as well as travel letters written by Joseph to his cousin Miranda B. Merwin.
The fourth and final section of correspondence covers the years between approximately 1915 and 1960 (Boxes 10-14, folders 324-419) and reflects the changes in the lives of the Roe children at this time. Lillie resigned as Field Secretary in 1913. She remained interested in mission work, but her letters are increasingly devoted to personal matters, especially to her ill-health. Her daughter Elizabeth Merwin Page Harris, called Bee, becomes a frequent correspondent of both Joseph and Mary Wickham Roe in the late 1920's, as her mother's health fails. These letters contain news of family financial arrangements and descriptions of her literary work. The letters of Lillie's younger daughter Marjorie Page Schauffler, called Marnie, are mainly brief, personal notes.
Mary Wickham Roe's correspondence also demonstrates her changing interests. After the death of Walter Clark Roe in 1913, she remained at Colony until 1932, and worked to further Protestant evangelization efforts in the United States and Latin America. Correspondents include Marcia Snyder, Anna Bayard Hawley, Charles Henry Lathrop, L.D. Collingwood, and Henry Turner. There are some letters from relatives, particularly William Edgar Roe, his daughter Caroline Clark Roe, and Henry Wickham Quinan. Topics include Mary's journeys to Central and South America, the mission field, and general religious themes. There are fewer letters after her retirement to California and most of these are personal notes written by Bee and Henry Wickham Quinan.
Joseph Wickham Roe remarried in 1915, and this final section contains letters of his wife, Mary Lambertson Roe, and her daughter, Betty Lambertson Pratt. Most of these are brief and personal. There is relatively little business correspondence, with the exception of several 1922 letters by Orville and Katherine Wright concerning an aviation film. Another subject of interest to Joseph Wickham Roe was genealogy. Beginning about 1915, he corresponds about the histories of the Roe, Wickham, Ludlow, and Brewster families. Correspondents include Clarence Torrey, Sarah Stebbins, Anna D. Roe Keith, Horace Halley, and Olga Starrett Chambers. Most of the letters from the last years of his life are brief notes written by Bee, with occasional letters from Marnie.
Many other topics are covered in the correspondence. For example, researchers can find a great deal of material on European travel in 1879; 1887, 1898, and 1902; on family reactions to death in 1873, 1889, 1897, 1903, and 1906; and on the difficulty of retiring in 1895, 1905, and 1931. The Roe family correspondence, especially when used in conjunction with the Wickham Family Papers, provides an interesting view of family and social life in nineteenth and early twentieth century America.
Series II, Family Papers, is housed in Boxes 18-29 of the Roe Family Papers and consists of a variety of materials by, about, or collected by members of the Roe family. The collection includes genealogical materials on the Brewer, Dresser, Ludlow, Roe, and Wickham families; financial records of James Gilbert Roe; reviews of novels by Edward Payson Roe and a short story, "Elder Strong Speaks Rather Strongly", also by Roe; a folder of sermon notes by Caroline Powell Roe Landon; obituaries of Peter Roe; newspaper clippings, poetry, and scrapbooks; and seven folders of memorabilia.
Material on Alfred Cox Roe and Emma Wickham Roe can be found in Boxes 18-20. The collection contains his chaplain's records and reports from 186-165, and two folders of articles about his war experiences; a folder of notes and reports on his work in New York City as a missionary for the American Christian Commission; "Street Talks" he delivered when pastor in Lowell, Massachusetts; and records from his ministerial career. There are also several folders of lecture notes, newspaper clippings, and other papers, including an article on "Hawthorne and his Teachings", published in 1888. The Roe Addition contains two drafts of his unpublished manuscript, "Rabboni: A Story of Jesus and His Friends". Material on Emma Wickham Roe includes an 1846 composition book, memorabilia of S.F.B. Morse, estate papers, and an obituary.
Boxes 20-21 contain the papers of Joseph Wickham Roe. These provide much information about his estate. (See also the Roe Addition, Boxes 158-160.) Also included are school compositions, reports, and other papers.
The papers of Mary Abigail Roe are located in Boxes 21-26. Much of this material is related to her teaching career. The papers also contain a typescript of "Recollections of the Roe Family"; reviews of two of her novels; six folders of other writings by Mary Abigail Roe; scrapbooks, clippings, and pamphlets; and a presentation copy of A. Moss Merwin's "The Drift from Rome", as well as an obituary of the author.
Boxes 26-29 contain the personal papers of Mary Wickham Roe and Walter Clark Roe. In addition to financial records, Mary Wickham Roe's papers include magazine and newspaper clippings, poetry, pamphlets, and obituaries. There are three folders of miscellaneous writings and five of Bible stories written with Walter Clark Roe. These papers also include biographical notes, obituaries, financial records, lecture notes, and the manuscript of his article, "Switzerland".
Series III, Diaries, fills Boxes 30-36, and contains diaries of several members of the Roe family. Alfred Cox Roe's diaries run from 1856-1900, and most of the brief daily entries are in shorthand. Mary Abigail Roe's 1879 diary is a record of her European tour. The diaries of Joseph Wickham Roe (1884, 1902-1960) contain short daily entries, usually professional in nature. Much information concerning the early years of Colony mission can be found in the Colony journals of Mary Wickham Roe. Topics in her later diaries include family news, details of her lecture tours, and her trips to Central and South America. Walter Clark Roe's diaries also provide material on the mission at Colony. The 1908-1909 diaries mention his work with the Ft. Sill Apaches.
Sermons by Alfred Cox Roe and Walter Clark Roe are found in Series IV. Most of. Alfred Cox Roe's sermons date from 1870-1874, the years of his ministerial service in Lowell, Massachusetts and Geneva, Galen, and Clyde, New York. Walter Clark Roe's sermons were almost all written for the churches he served in the Ft. Worth area from 1893-1897. There is one folder of mission sermons. The sermon fragments and sermon notes may also date from Colony.
Series V, Printed Works, contains both works written by and works owned by several members of the Roe family. Boxes 45-51 house a virtually complete collection of the novels of Edward Payson Roe. Other works in this series authored by Roes include Joseph Wickham Roe's Inventors and Engineers of Old New Haven; two novels by Mary Abigail Roe, and her Reminiscences of E.P. Roe (Roe Addition, Box 162); and Mary E. Roe's The Count of Elsinore; or, Valdemar the Baltic Rover. Boxes 53-57 contain a variety of printed items. Books not otherwise identified were probably collected by Mary Wickham Roe.
Series VI, Family Photographs, fills Boxes 58-66 of the Roe Family Papers. Photographs of people, mostly of family members and family friends, are found in Boxes 58-63; photographs of places in Boxes 64-66.